Chapter 22. Merry Christmas.
At length, towards noon, upon the final dismissal of the ship's rigors, and
after the Peekquad had been hauled for out from the wararf, and after the ever
thoughtful charity had come off in a whaleboat, with her last gift, a night
cap for Stub, the second mate, her brother-in-law, and a spare Bible for
the steward. After all this, the two captains, Pelleg and Bildad, issued from
the cabin, and turning to the chief mate, Pelleg said, "Now, Mr. Starbucks,
are you sure everything is all right?
Captain Ahab is all ready. Just spoke to him. Nothing more to be got from shore,
eh?" Well, call all hands then. Muster am here, Blaste.
No need of profane words, however great the hurry, Pelleg, said. Bildad, but
away with thee, friend Starbucks, and do our bidding. How now, here, upon the
very point of starting for the voyage, Captain Pelleg and Captain Bildad were
going it with a high hand on the quarter deck, just as if they were to be joint
commanders at sea, as well as to all appearances in port. And as for Captain
Ahab, no sign of him was yet to be seen.
Only they said he was in the cabin. But then the idea was that his presence was
by no means necessary in getting the ship underway and steering her well out
to sea. Indeed, as that was not at all his proper business, but the pilots, and
as he was not yet completely recovered, so they said. Therefore, Captain Ahab
stayed below. And all this seemed natural enough, especially as in the
merchant service, many captains never show themselves on deck for a
considerable time after heaving up the anchor, but remain over the cabin table,
having a farewell merrymaking with their shore friends before they quit the ship
for good with the pilot.
But there was not much chance to think over the matter, for Captain Pelleg was
now all alive. He seemed to do most of the talking and commanding and not
buildad. Aft here you sons of bachelors he cried as the sailors lingered at the
main mast. Mr. Starbucks drive them a strike the tent there was the next
order. As I hinted before this whale bone marquee was never pitched except in
port and on board the peekquad for 30 years the order to strike the tent was
well known to be the next thing to heaving up the anchor. Man, the cap
stand. Blood and thunder. Jump, was the next command, and the crew sprang for
the hand spikes. Now, in getting underway, the station generally occupied
by the pilot, is the forward part of the ship. And here Bildad, who with Pelleg
be it known, in addition to his other officers, was one of the licensed pilots
of the port, he being suspected to have got himself made a pilot in order to
save the Nantucket pilot fee to all the ships he was concerned in, for he never
piloted any other craft. Bildad, I say, might now be seen actively engaged in
looking over the boughs for the approaching anchor, and at intervals
singing what seemed a dismal stave of somdi to cheer the hands at the
windless, who roared forth some sort of chorus about the girls in Bubble Alley
with a hearty goodwill. Nevertheless, not 3 days previous, Bildad had told
them that no profane songs would be allowed on board the Peekquad,
particularly in getting underway, and Charity, his sister, had placed a small
choiced copy of Watts in each seaman's birth.
Meantime, overseeing the other part of the ship, Captain Pelleg ripped and
swore a stern in the most frightful manner. I almost thought he would sink
the ship before the anchor could be got up. Involuntarily, I paused on my hand
spike and told Quiqu to do the same, thinking of the perils, we both ran in
starting on the voyage was such a devil for a pilot. I was comforting myself,
however, with the thought that in pious Bildad might be found some salvation, in
spite of his 777th lay, when I felt a sudden sharp poke in
my rear, and turning round was horrified at the apparition of Captain Pelleg in
the act of withdrawing his leg from my immediate vicinity.
That was my first kick.
"Is that the way they heave in the merchant service?" he roared. "Spring,
thou sheep head! Spring and break thy backbone. Why don't you spring, I say
all of you. Spring, Quhog, spring, thou chap with a red whisker. Spring there,
Scotch cap. Spring, thou green pants.
Spring, I say all of you, and spring your eyes out. And so saying, he moved
along the windless here and there, using his leg very freely, while imperturbable
kept leading off with his salad. Thinks I, Captain Pelleg, must have been
drinking something today.
At last the anchor was up, the sails were set, and off we glided. It was a
short, cold Christmas, and as the short northern day merged into night, we found
ourselves almost broad upon the wintry ocean, whose freezing spray cased us in
ice as in polished armor. The long rows of teeth on the bulwarks glistened in
the moonlight, and like the white ivory tusks of some huge elephant, vast
curving icicles depended from the boughs. Lank Bildad as pilot headed the
first watch, and Ever and Anan, as the old craft deep dived into the green
seas, and sent the shivering frost all over her, and the winds howled and the
cordage rang, his steady notes were heard. Sweet fields beyond the swelling
flood stand dressed in living green. So to the Jews old Canaan stood, while
Jordan rolled between.
Never did those sweet words sound more sweetly to me than them. They were full
of hope and fruition. In spite of this frigid winter night in the boisterous
Atlantic, spite of my wet feet and wetter jacket, there was yet, it then
seemed to me, many a pleasant haven in store, and messes and glades so
eternally vernal that the grass shot up by the spring, untrodden, unwilted,
remains at midsummer.
At last we gained such an offing that the two pilots were needed no longer.
The stout sailboat that had accompanied us began ranging alongside.
It was curious and not unpleasing how Pelleg and Bildad were affected at this
juncture, especially Captain Bildad, for loathed to depart yet, very loathed to
leave for good a ship bound on so long and perilous a voyage beyond both stormy
capes, a ship in which some thousands of his hard-earned dollars were invested. A
ship in which an old shipmate sailed as captain, a man almost as old as he, once
more starting to encounter all the terrors of the pitilous jaw. Loathed to
say goodbye to a thing so every way brimful of every interest to him, poor
old Bildad lingered long, paced the deck with anxious strides, ran down into the
cabin to speak another farewell word there, again came on deck, and looked to
windward, looked towards the wide and endless waters, only bounded by the far
off, unseen eastern continents, looked toward the land, looked a loft, looked
right and left, looked everywhere and nowhere, and at last mechanically
coiling a rope upon its pin, convulsively grasped stout Pelleg by the
hand, and holding up a lantern for the moment, stood gazing heroically in his
face, as much to say, "Nevertheless, friend Pelleg, I can stand it. Yes, I
can." As for Pelleg himself, he took it more like a philosopher. But for all his
philosophy there was a tear twinkling in his eye when the lantern came too near.
And he too did not a little run from cabin to deck. Now a word below. Now a
word was Starbucks the chief mate. But at last he turned to his comrade with a
final sort of look about him. Captain Bildad, come old shipmate. We must go
back the mainard there. Boy. Stand by to come close alongside now. Careful.
Careful. Come, Bill. Dad boy, say your last. Luck to you, Starbucks. Luck to
you, Mr. Stub. Luck to you, Mr. Flask.
Goodbye and good luck to you all. And this day, 3 years, I'll have a hot
supper smoking for you in old Nantucket.
Hurrah and away.
God bless you, and have you in his holy keeping, men, murmured old Bildad almost incoherently.
I hope you'll have fine weather now so that Captain Ahab may soon be moving
among you. A pleasant sun is all he needs and you'll have plenty of them in
the tropic voyage you go. Be careful in the hunt, you mates. Don't stave the
boats needlessly, you harpineers. Good white cedar plank is raised full 3%
within the year. Don't forget your prayers either. Mr. Starbucks, mind that
Cooper. Don't waste the spare staves.
Oh, the sail needles are in the green locker. Don't wail it too much on the
Lord's days, men. But don't miss a fair chance either. That's rejecting heaven's
good gifts. Have an eye to the molasses, tears, Mr. Stub. It was a little leaky,
I thought. If you touch at the islands, Mr. Flask, beware of fornication.
Goodbye. Goodbye. Don't keep that cheese too long down in the hold, Mr.
Starbucks. It'll spoil. Be careful with the butter. 20 cents the pound it was.
And mind you, if Come Captain Billad, stop pavering away. And with that,
Pelleg hurried him over the side, and both dropped into the boat. Ship and
boat diverged. The cold, damp night breeze blew between. A screaming gull
flew overhead. The two hulls wildly rolled. We gave three heavy-hearted
cheers and blindly plunged like fate into the lone Atlantic.